{"tossups": [{"question": "The \u201cTwin Sister\u201d cannons were used in this battle, in which Deaf Smith was ordered to destroy Vince\u2019s Bridge during this battle and Mirabeau Lamar provided reinforcements. The rallying cries\u201cRemember Goliad\u201d and \u201cRemember the Alamo\u201d were used at this battle, where Santa Anna was captured. Sam Houston won, for ten points, what twenty-minute battle that ended the Mexican-American War?", "answer": "Battle of<b> San Jacinto</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This leader ordered the execution of Raynald de Chatillon [sha-tee-YOHN]. King Baldwin IV repelled an attack from this man at the Battle of Montgisard [mohn-gee-SAHR]. He was also defeated in the Battle of Arsuf after the winning side had sieged Acre [AH-kur]. This founder of the Ayyubid Dynasty captured Jerusalem after the Battle of Hattin, which prompted the Third Crusade. For ten points, name this Muslim Kurdish ruler whose main enemy was Richard the Lionhearted.", "answer": "<b> Saladin</b> (or<b> Salah ad-Din</b> Yusuf ibn Ayyub)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One side\u2019s attack on Saarbrucken early in this war showed the value of their Chassepot [sha-say-poh] rifles, but was defeated at the Battle of Wissembourg [VISS-em-boorg]. The Army of Chalons was formed during this war to rescue troops encircled at Metz, and this war was ended by the Treaty of Frankfurt. The Second Empire was dissolved after a defeat at Sedan in this war. For ten points, name this war that resulted in the formation of the German Empire and the defeat of Napoleon III.", "answer": "<b> Franco-Prussian</b> War (accept<b> Franco-German</b> War; accept<b> War of 1870</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This body of water\u2019s southern shore was home to the Achaemenid province of Hyrcania. Astrakhan lies on a river delta that empties into this body of water, where demand for caviar has caused the Beluga sturgeon to be overfished. The world\u2019s first offshore oil platform was built in this sea near Baku, Azerbaijan. For ten points, name this salty inland sea, considered the largest lake in the world.", "answer": "<b> Caspian</b> Sea", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "James Monroe was one of only two Americans wounded during this battle. The losing commander at this engagement ignored a message urging him to build fortifications found in his pocket after his death here; that commander was Johann Rall. The winning commander of this battle withdrew to prepare for the ensuing Battle of Princeton. For ten points, name this 1776 battle fought in New Jersey where, on Christmas night, George Washington\u2019s troops crossed the Delaware River.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Trenton</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s death was most likely in revenge of his killing of Jesus Herrera. His defeat at the Battle of Celaya by Alvaro Obregon led him to escape to Chihuahua. The assassination of Francesco Madero led this man to form a military band known as the Division of the North. This man\u2019s raid in Columbus led an unsuccessful expedition by John Pershing to capture him. For ten points, name this early 20th century Mexican bandit.", "answer": "<b> Pancho Villa</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Edwin Stanton and Abraham Lincoln were lawyers for John Manny, who was sued by this man for patent infringement. In 1902, this man\u2019s company merged with the Deering Harvester Company to create the International Harvester Company. This man is credited with inventing a device that harvested grain using moving blades on a platform. For ten points, name this inventor of the mechanical reaper.", "answer": "Cyrus<b> McCormick</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This hero and his friend Pirithous were once stuck to a bench in the underworld after attempting to kidnap Hades\u2019 wife Persephone. This hero\u2019s son Hippolytus rejected the advances of his stepmother, Phaedra. This hero\u2019s father, Aegeus, threw himself off a cliff in despair after this hero returned without changing his black sails to white. For ten points, name this hero, the legendary founder of Athens who defeated the Minotaur in the labyrinth.", "answer": "<b> Theseus</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "The publication of a pamphlet espousing this concept caused Percy Shelley to be expelled from Oxford. A 1927 speech at Battersea Town Hall arguing for this concept questioned the idea of everlasting punishment as a defect in the moral character of Christ. Bertrand Russell\u2019s \u201cWhy I Am Not a Christian\u201dargued in favor of, for ten points, what philosophical concept that opposes the existence of gods?", "answer": "<b> atheism</b> (accept word forms; accept descriptions of<b> not believing in god(s)</b>; do not accept agnosticism)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader established a national chain of stores called Mercal and quipped that a podium \u201cstill smelled of sulfur\u201dafter calling George W. Bush \u201cthe devil.\u201d In 2013, this leader entered his fourth term while in Cuba for cancer treatment. For ten points, name this Socialist who ruled from 2002 to 2013 as President of Venezuela.", "answer": "Hugo Rafael<b> Chavez</b> Frias", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 1998, West Windsor Township celebrated the 50th anniversary of this event, which occurred as part of The Mercury Theatre on Air\u2019s Halloween special. This event opened with Dan Seymour stating that it was a dramatization, but this event\u2019s fake news bulletins led people to believe aliens were invading earth. For ten points, name this event in which Orson Welles caused mass hysteria by narrating an adaptation of an HG Wells novel.", "answer": "Radio<b> broadcast</b> of The<b> War of the Worlds</b> (prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler ignited a rebellion after appointing Yuri Dolgoruki to round up fugitive peasants in lands led by Kondraty Bulavin. This ruler signed the Treaty of Constantinople with Mustafa II, which led to this ruler creating his country\u2019s first navy base on the Sea of Azov. He instituted a beard tax for the boyars and traveled incognito to observe a Dutch shipyard as part of his Grand Embassy. For ten points, name this \u201cgreat\u201d Czar whose modernization included the founding of Saint Petersburg.", "answer": "<b> Peter I</b> or<b> Peter the Great</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Neil Finn sang that this concept is \u201cwithin\u201d and \u201cwithout\u201d in the opening lyrics of\u201cDon\u2019t Dream It\u2019s Over.\u201d Paul McCartney wrote a song with this title while in a grounded</b> <b>plane in New York during the (+)</b> <b>September 11th attacks. It is \u201cjust another word for</b> <b>nothing left to lose\u201d in Janis Joplin\u2019s \u201cMe and Bobby McGee,\u201d and K\u2019Naan sang \u201cthey call (*) </b> me\u201d this, \u201cjust like a wavin\u2019 flag\u201d. For ten points, name this political concept, the liberty to exert choice and a lack of oppression.", "answer": "<b> freedom</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man presided over Samuel Chase\u2019s impeachment trial, the first in American history.</b> <b>James Wilkinson informed Thomas Jefferson of a potential (+)</b> <b>conspiracy created by</b> <b>this politician to form a nation in Southwestern United States under land leased by Spain. Thomas Jefferson\u2019s (*) </b> first Vice President was, for ten points, what man who gained infamy at Weehawken, New Jersey when he killed Alexander Hamilton in a duel?", "answer": "Aaron<b> Burr</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This artist began his career with historical images like</b><em><b> The Misfortunes of the City of </b><b>Orleans</b></em><b>, and painted his aunt with her daughters and husband, Baron Gennaro (+) Bellelli. His first work to be bought by a museum shows his uncle, Michel Musson\u2019s, title</b><em><b> Cotton </b><b>Office in New Orleans</b></em><b>. A man wearing a black hat and a woman in a white dress sit in a caf\u00b4e with a glass of the title (*)</b> green beverage in this artist\u2019s<em> L\u2019Absinthe</em>. For ten points, name this French artist who painted many depictions of young ballerinas.", "answer": "Edgar<b> Degas</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}